A Guide to the Papers of Paul T. Schweitzer 1955-1976
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of Paul T. Schweitzer 1955-1976
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 16
3 Hollinger Document cases, 1 Hollinger Drop-Front print box; 2.5 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to researchers without restrictions. Questions on literary property rights should be directed to the Special Collections Librarian.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Edna S. Schweitzer, April 7, 1976
Accession No. A77-23
Biographical/Historical Information
Paul T. Schweitzer was born on August 1, 1903, on a farm near Malta, Illinois. Three years later the family moved to Arizona where his father became manager of a cattle ranch outside of Tucson. Several years later the elder Mr. Schweitzer moved into Tucson where he founded the Schweitzer Machine Company which specialized in water pumps. The family moved to Los Angeles in 1918 where the younger Mr. Schweitzer completed high school and went to work for a mortgage and loan company. He remained with the firm until its dissolution in 1935. He then traveled to Washington, D.C. where he opened a branch of Layne-Atlantic Company, a firm that develops and engineers large-scale water distribution systems. Joining company headquarters in Norfolk in 1939, he was made vice president and ultimately chairman of the board.
Mr. Schweitzer's contributions as a businessman and civic leader to the recent history of Norfolk were most distinguished. He was appointed to the Norfolk School Board in 1952, elected chairman in 1955 and served in this capacity until he was appointed to the Norfolk City Council in March 1960. During his years as chairman of the school board, Norfolk experienced the massive resistance crisis. From September 1958 until January 1959 three white high schools and three white junior high schools in the city were closed under Virginia law by order of Governor J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. because the schools were under court order to integrate. Schweitzer was in the forefront of those who worked to have the schools reopened. Mr. Schweitzer was re-elected as chairman of the reorganized Norfolk School Board in July 1959. In the following year he was appointed to the Norfolk City Council to replace George R. Abbott who resigned. Schweitzer was elected in 1960 and re-elected in 1964. He was defeated for re-election in 1968.
Mr. Schweitzer's civic activities were numerous. He served on the board of trustees of Lynchburg College from 1957 until May 1976. As chairman of the board he was involved in launching the college's Partnership for Progress development program in 1966. According to Dr. Carey Brewer, president of Lynchburg College, the Partnership of Progress program which raised more than $10 million was "perhaps the major advancement in the total history of the College." Mr. Schweitzer was also a member of the board of directors and the president of the Norfolk Central YMCA, a member of the National Council of the YMCA and chairman of the recreation and education division of the United Communities Council of Social Agencies. He was also vice president of the Tidewater Virginia Development Council, Norfolk region, a member of the board of directors of the Norfolk General Hospital and vice chairman of the board of trustees of Virginia Wesleyan College. He was also chairman of the board of deacons and elder emeritus of First Christian Church.
Mr. Schweitzer attained a respected position in the business community. In addition to his position at Layne Atlantic Company, Mr. Schweitzer was director of the Lakewood Water Company in Myrtle Beach, South Carolina and of the Belvedere Water Company in Glen Burnie, Maryland. He was the author of several technical papers on ground water which were published in the Journal of the American Water Works Association. He was a member of the Society of American Military Engineers.
Mr. Schweitzer was married in 1940 to the former Edna Ilene Stillman of Alexandria, Virginia. They had three children, Mark, Betty Mae and Kay Marie.
Scope and Content Information
Paul T. Schweitzer was a Norfolk businessman who served on the Norfolk School Board from 1952 to 1960 and as a member of the Norfolk City Council from 1960 to 1968. His greatest prominence as a civic leader came during the "massive resistance" crisis when six Norfolk schools which were under court order to admit black students were closed by Governor J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. His papers consist of six series: correspondence dating from 1955 to 1968 concerned principally with Mr. Schweitzer's service on the school board during the massive resistance crisis and his service on the city council; legal documents including transcripts of court proceedings and oaths; publications dating from 1956 to 1961; newspaper clippings dating from 1957 to 1976; photographs including group pictures of the Norfolk School Board, Norfolk City Council and Norfolk Operation Understanding Group I; miscellaneous material including an outside proof of a newspaper advertisement-petition urging the reopening of the closed schools; and over-sized material including scrapbooks which contain principally newspaper clippings with some correspondence and political campaign materials.
Arrangement
Documents are arranged chronologically within the first 3 series: Series I: Correspondence; Series II: Legal Documents; Series III: Publications. Also included are Series IV: Photographs, Series V: Miscellaneous, and Series VI: Oversized Materials.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence March 1957-July 1958 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence August-September 1958 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence September-October 1958 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence January 1959 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence February 1959 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence March-May 1959 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence October 1959 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence February 1960 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence March 1950 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence May-June 1960 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence July 1960 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence July 1961 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence December 1961-May 1966 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence June-July 1968 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence August-September 1968 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series II: Legal Documents
  - Legal Documents 1958-1962 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series III: Publications
  - Sub Series A: Miscellaneous
    - Tidewater's Guardian October 1957 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Business Week February 22,1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Time September 22, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Life September 22, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Business Week October 4, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Business Week November 15, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Time February 2,1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Time February 9, 1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Better Schools February 1960 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Virginia School Boards Association Newsletter March 1960 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - National Civic Review February 1961 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sub Series B: Newspaper Clippings
    - Newspaper Clippings February 1957 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper Clippings July 1957 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Newspaper Clippings August 1-20, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper Clippings August 21-31, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper Clippings September 1-7, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Newspaper Clippings September 8-15, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Newspaper Clippings September 16-30, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Newspaper Clippings October 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Newspaper Clippings November 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Newspaper Clippings January 1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Newspaper Clippings February 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings May 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings July 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings August 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings September 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper Clippings October 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings November 1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings February 1960 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper Clippings July-August 1968 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper Clippings (copies) November 1976 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper Clippings (undated) (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Photographs: Norfolk City Council (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Photographs: Norfolk Operation Understanding Group I (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photographs: Norfolk School Board (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series V: Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous Material: Program, Advertisement, Campaign Brochure, etc. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 15)
- Oversized Materials
  - Two Scrapbooks containing principally newspaper clippings (Box-folder Box 4)
  - Two Newspaper tabloid sections (Box-folder Box 4)
  - Two Certificates (Box-folder Box 4)
  - One Print (Box-folder Box 4)
  - One mounted newspaper article (Box-folder Box 4)